A Guide to the United Confederate Veterans Collection, 1893-1938: SC 0133
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
United Confederate Veterans Collection,
1893-1938
Special Collections, James Madison University
United Confederate Veterans
SC 0133
.4 cubic feet; 1 box
The United Confederate Veterans Collection, 1893-1938, consists of nine folders and two ledger books pertaining to the United Confederate Veterans (UCV) organization.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
This collection is on deposit from the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society.
Other Formats Available
This collection is also available on Microfilm #1488 and may be used instead of the originals. The microfilm is available in Special Collections.
Administrative History
The United Confederate Veterans is a national organization established in 1890 for Confederate veterans, their sons, and their close relatives.
Scope and Content
The United Confederate Veterans Collection, 1893-1938, consists of nine folders and two ledger books pertaining to the United Confederate Veterans (UCV) organization. The collection includes letters from national and state level headquarters of the UCV and documents from S.B. Gibbons Camp 438, the Harrisonburg chapter of the UCV.
Series 1: National and State Headquarters documents, 1896-1938, contains papers which were sent from the national headquarters in New Orleans, and the state headquarters in Petersburg and Norfolk, Virginia. These papers consist of general orders to all camps, receipts of dues from headquarters, circular letters and notices for state and national reunions and conventions.
Series 2: Papers of S.B. Gibbons Camp 438, 1893-1927, is comprised of documents pertaining to the Harrisonburg UCV chapter. Included in this series are letters from other UCV chapters or "camps," letters from members of Camp 438, and letters from various businesses. Also included are membership rolls and dues records; several lists of applicants for the Southern Cross of Honor, a medal given to Confederate veterans; two ledger books, each containing minutes of meetings, and three folders which contain enclosures from the ledger books and minutes of meeting not recorded in the ledger books. In the folder containing enclosures from the first ledger book is a listing of soldiers killed and wounded in action around Orange Court House, Virginia, in 1864. Also included is a roll of Woodson's Company, McNiell's Squadron of the Partisan Rangers, C.S.A.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
Series 1: National and State Headquarters documents, 1896-1938
Series 2: Papers of S.B. Gibbons Camp 438, 1893-1927
Index Terms
Subjects:
United Confederate Veterans -- Records and correspondence; United Confederate Veterans. Virginia Division. -- Records and correspondence; United Confederate Veterans. Virginia Division. S. B. Gibbons Camp No. 438 (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- Records and correspondence; Confederate States of America -- History -- Societies, etc.; Confederate States of America. Army -- Biography; Confederate States of America -- History, Military -- Sources; Confederate States of America. Army. McNeill Partisan Rangers. Woodson's Company -- Sources; Orange Court House (Va.), Battle of, 1864; Harrisonburg (Va.) -- History -- Sources; Rockingham County (Va.) -- History -- Sources; Orange County (Va.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Registers; United States -- Armed Forces -- Biography; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Societies, etc. -- Confederate; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History -- Sources; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources; Registers (lists)
- Series 1: National and State Headquarters documents, 1896-1938
  - National Headquarters Papers, 1896-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - State Headquarters Papers, 1898-1926, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series 2: Papers of S.B. Gibbons Camp 438, 1893-1927
  - Letters from other UCV Camps, 1901-1912, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Camp members, various businesses, 1897-1924, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Membership rolls, lists of dues records, lists of Southern Cross of Honor Applicants, 1896-1913, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1897-1907, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ledger Book 1: Minutes of Camp 438, 1893-1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ledger Book 2: Minutes of Camp 438, 1905-1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Enclosures from Ledger Book 1, 1893-1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Enclosures from Ledger Book 2, 1905-1927 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, Records of Business Conducted at Meetings, 1897-1904, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)